[
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which one of the following periods is also known as Chalcolithic Age?",
        "answer": "Copper Age",
        "choices": [
            "Copper Age",
            "Old Stone Age",
            "New Stone Age",
            "Iron Age"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Indus Civilisation existed in",
        "answer": "Proto-Historic age",
        "choices": [
            "Proto-Historic age",
            "Pre-Historic age",
            "Historic age",
            "Post-Historic age"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "The earliest evidence of animal domestication and agriculture in India has come from",
        "answer": "Mehrgarh",
        "choices": [
            "Mehrgarh",
            "Harappa",
            "Lothal",
            "Diamabad"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "The earliest evidence of rice cultivation in Ganga valley comes from",
        "answer": "Lahuradewa",
        "choices": [
            "Lahuradewa",
            "Mehrgarh",
            "Lothal",
            "Diamabad"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which colour was commonly used in the Harappan Pottery?",
        "answer": "Red-Black",
        "choices": [
            "Red-Black",
            "Yellow",
            "Green",
            "Blue-Grey"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "In which of the following Harappan cities, furrows of ploughed fields have been found?",
        "answer": "Kalibangan",
        "choices": [
            "Kalibangan",
            "Dholavira",
            "Mohenjodaro",
            "Lothal"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "In which of the following Harappan sites, terracotta of plough has been found?",
        "answer": "Banawali",
        "choices": [
            "Banawali",
            "Dholavira",
            "Kalibangan",
            "Lothal"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "What is the most significant feature of the Indus Valley Civilisation?",
        "answer": "Use of burnt bricks",
        "choices": [
            "Use of burnt bricks",
            "Fine true arches",
            "Buildings of worship",
            "Art & Architecture"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which of the following animals was not known to the people of Indus Valley Civilisation",
        "answer": "Horse",
        "choices": [
            "Horse",
            "Humped Bull (Zebu)",
            "Deer",
            "Elephant"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which of the following is Harappan Port",
        "answer": "Lothal",
        "choices": [
            "Lothal",
            "Diamabad",
            "Nagapattinam",
            "Mahasthangarh"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which of the following is the largest Harappan site in India",
        "answer": "Rakhigarhi",
        "choices": [
            "Rakhigarhi",
            "Mohenjodaro",
            "Lothal",
            "Kalibangan"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which of the following is the largest Harappan site",
        "answer": "Mohenjodaro",
        "choices": [
            "Mohenjodaro",
            "Rakhigarhi",
            "Lothal",
            "Kalibangan"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which of the following is the western most Harappan site",
        "answer": "Sutkagendor",
        "choices": [
            "Sutkagendor",
            "Shortugai",
            "Alamgirpur",
            "Diamabad"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which of the following is the eastern most Harappan site",
        "answer": "Alamgirpur",
        "choices": [
            "Alamgirpur",
            "Shortugai",
            "Suktagendor",
            "Diamabad"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which of the following is the northern most Harappan site",
        "answer": "Shortugai",
        "choices": [
            "Shortugai",
            "Alamgirpur",
            "Suktagendor",
            "Diamabad"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which of the following is the southern most Harappan site",
        "answer": "Diamabad",
        "choices": [
            "Diamabad",
            "Alamgirpur",
            "Suktagendor",
            "Shortugai"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which of the following Harappan site is associated with trade in Lapis Lazuli",
        "answer": "Shortugai",
        "choices": [
            "Shortugai",
            "Sutkagendor",
            "Surkotada",
            "Manda"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which of the following is a Harappan site in Gujarat",
        "answer": "Lothal",
        "choices": [
            "Lothal",
            "Dabarkot",
            "Kalibangan",
            "Rakhigarhi"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Who among the following was not associated with the excavation of Harappa and Mohenjodaro?",
        "answer": "V A Smith",
        "choices": [
            "V A Smith",
            "R D Banerjee",
            "K N Dikshit",
            "M S Vats"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "According to report of IIT Kharagpur study group, continous low rainfall for how many years was the cause of fall of the Indus Valley civilisation?",
        "answer": "900 years",
        "choices": [
            "900 years",
            "600 years",
            "700 years",
            "800 years"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "When did the use of Iron begin in Indian Subcontinent?",
        "answer": "Around 3000 years ago",
        "choices": [
            "Around 3000 years ago",
            "Around 6000 years ago",
            "Around 9000 years ago",
            "Around 10000 years ago"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which mandala of Rig Veda is completely dedicated to 'Soma'?",
        "answer": "Ninth Mandala",
        "choices": [
            "Ninth Mandala",
            "Seventh Mandala",
            "Eighth Mandala",
            "Tenth Mandala"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Name the ancient site outside India from where inscription containing Rigvedic dieties names has been found",
        "answer": "Boghazkoi",
        "choices": [
            "Boghazkoi",
            "Babylon",
            "Gonur Tepe",
            "Ur"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Famous Battle of Ten Kings was fought on the bank of river:",
        "answer": "Parushni",
        "choices": [
            "Parushni",
            "Ganga",
            "Brahmputra",
            "Kaveri"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "In which Mandala of Rigveda, Battle of Ten Kings is mentioned",
        "answer": "Seventh Mandala",
        "choices": [
            "Seventh Mandala",
            "Eighth Mandala",
            "Tenth Mandala",
            "Ninth Mandala"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "In which Mandala of Rigveda, Gayatri Mantra is mentioned",
        "answer": "Third Mandala",
        "choices": [
            "Third Mandala",
            "Eighth Mandala",
            "Seventh Mandala",
            "Ninth Mandala"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "In which book Gayatri Mantra is found",
        "answer": "Rig Veda",
        "choices": [
            "Rig Veda",
            "Upanishad",
            "Bhagwatgita",
            "Ramayana"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Gayatri Mantra is dedicated to which diety",
        "answer": "Sun",
        "choices": [
            "Sun",
            "Parvati",
            "Shiva",
            "Indra"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "In which phase, the concept of untouchability was put clearly?",
        "answer": "Dharmashastra Phase",
        "choices": [
            "Dharmashastra Phase",
            "Rigvedic Phase",
            "Later Vedic Phase",
            "Later Gupta Phase"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which ancient Indian text, composed during the later Vedic period, contains philosophical hymns and discussions on cosmology and ethics?",
        "answer": "Upanishads",
        "choices": [
            "Upanishads",
            "Rigveda",
            "Yajurveda",
            "Samveda"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Where did Mahatma Buddha's Mahaparinirvana take place",
        "answer": "Khushi Nagar",
        "choices": [
            "Khushi Nagar",
            "Lumbini",
            "Kapilvastu",
            "Bodhgaya"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "The ruler of Suvarnabhumi, who founded a Buddhist monastery at Nalanda and requested Devapala through his ambassador to grant, five villages for its maintenance, was",
        "answer": "Balaputradeva",
        "choices": [
            "Balaputradeva",
            "Dharanindra",
            "Sangramadhanjaya",
            "Chudamanivarmana"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "At which place did Mahatma Buddha give his first Dharmachakkhapavathana?",
        "answer": "Sarnath",
        "choices": [
            "Sarnath",
            "Lumbini",
            "Khushi Nagar",
            "Kapilvastu"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Who got enlightenment in Bodh Gaya?",
        "answer": "Gautam Buddha",
        "choices": [
            "Gautam Buddha",
            "Mahavir Jain",
            "Smandhar Swami",
            "Parshvanath Swami"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Gautam Buddha gave his first sermon at",
        "answer": "Sarnath",
        "choices": [
            "Sarnath",
            "Vaishali",
            "Kaushambi",
            "Pavapuri"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which of the following rulers convened the fourth Buddhist Council in Kashmir?",
        "answer": "Kanishka",
        "choices": [
            "Kanishka",
            "Ashoka",
            "Ajatshatru",
            "kalashoka"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "A Buddhist Council during the reign of Kanishka was held at",
        "answer": "Kashmir",
        "choices": [
            "Kashmir",
            "Magadha",
            "Pataliputra",
            "Rajgriha"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Where was the third Buddhist Council held?",
        "answer": "Pataliputra",
        "choices": [
            "Pataliputra",
            "Sarnath",
            "Taxila",
            "Bodh Gaya"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "The third Buddhist Council was presided over by",
        "answer": "Moggaliputta-Tissa",
        "choices": [
            "Moggaliputta-Tissa",
            "Mahakassapa",
            "Vasumitra",
            "Ashvaghosha"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "In Indian art, the construction of Stupa, Chaitya and Vihara is related to which of the following?",
        "answer": "Buddhism",
        "choices": [
            "Buddhism",
            "Jainism",
            "Vaishanva sect",
            "Shaiva sect"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Mahabodhi temple has been built at Bodh Gaya where",
        "answer": "Gautam Buddha received enlightenment",
        "choices": [
            "Gautam Buddha received enlightenment",
            "Gautam Buddha was born",
            "Gautam Buddha gave his first sermon",
            "Gautam Buddha passed away"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "The present Bodhi Vriksha in Bodh Gaya belongs to which generation of family",
        "answer": "Fifth",
        "choices": [
            "Fifth",
            "Fourth",
            "Third",
            "Sixth"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "After the Mahaparinirvana of Lord Buddha, the first Buddhist council was held at",
        "answer": "Rajgriha (Rajgir)",
        "choices": [
            "Rajgriha (Rajgir)",
            "Pataliputra (Patna)",
            "Kundalvana (Kashmir)",
            "Vaishali"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Tripatikas are the sacred books of the",
        "answer": "Buddhists",
        "choices": [
            "Buddhists",
            "Jains",
            "Hindus",
            "Parsis"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which of the following buddhist literature is not grouped as Tripitaks",
        "answer": "Milind Panha",
        "choices": [
            "Milind Panha",
            "Sutta Pitaka",
            "Vinay Pitaka",
            "Abhidhamma Pitaka"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Where is the highest Vishwa Shanti Stupa located in Bihar",
        "answer": "Rajgir",
        "choices": [
            "Rajgir",
            "Vaishali",
            "Patna",
            "Nalanda"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Barabudur is the most wonderful Stupa in the world and its images and sculptures are the finest examples of",
        "answer": "Indo-Javanese Art",
        "choices": [
            "Indo-Javanese Art",
            "Indo-Tibetan Art",
            "Indo-Cambodian Art",
            "Indo-Champan Art"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Gautam Buddha was elevated to the position of God during the period of",
        "answer": "Kanishka",
        "choices": [
            "Kanishka",
            "Ashoka",
            "Chandragupta Vikramaditya",
            "Harsha"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Where is Odantipuri (Uddandapura) Mahavihar located?",
        "answer": "Bihar Sharif",
        "choices": [
            "Bihar Sharif",
            "Bhagalpur",
            "Nalanda",
            "Bengal"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Odantipuri (Uddandapura) Mahavihar was established by",
        "answer": "Gopal",
        "choices": [
            "Gopal",
            "Kumargupta",
            "Dharampala",
            "Ajatshatru"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Nalanda University was founded during the dynasty of",
        "answer": "Gupta",
        "choices": [
            "Gupta",
            "Kushan",
            "Maurya",
            "Pala"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Why was Nalanda University famous in the world?",
        "answer": "Buddhist Religious Philosophy",
        "choices": [
            "Buddhist Religious Philosophy",
            "Medical Science",
            "Philosophy",
            "Chemical Science"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Who was the founder of Nalanda University?",
        "answer": "Kumargupta",
        "choices": [
            "Kumargupta",
            "Chandragupta Vikramaditya",
            "Dharampala",
            "Pushyagupta"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Nav Nalanda Mahavihar is famous for",
        "answer": "Pali Research Centre",
        "choices": [
            "Pali Research Centre",
            "Museum",
            "Hsuan-Tsang Memorial",
            "Birth place of Mahavir"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which one of the following is not common between Buddhism and Jainism?",
        "answer": "Self-Mortification",
        "choices": [
            "Self-Mortification",
            "Ahimsa",
            "Indifference to Vedas",
            "Rejection of Rituals"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "The painting of Bodhisattva Padmapani is located at",
        "answer": "Ajanta",
        "choices": [
            "Ajanta",
            "Ellora",
            "Rajgir",
            "Barabar Hills"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Where was Mahavira Swami born",
        "answer": "Kundgram (Vaishali)",
        "choices": [
            "Kundgram (Vaishali)",
            "Pataliputra (Patna)",
            "Rajgriha (Rajgir)",
            "Lumbini"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Mahavir Jain breathed his last at",
        "answer": "Pavapuri",
        "choices": [
            "Pavapuri",
            "Kundgram (Vaishali)",
            "Rajgriha (Rajgir)",
            "Kapilvastu"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "The salvation place of Mahavirji, the originator of Jain religion, is located at",
        "answer": "Jrimbhikagrama (Jamui)",
        "choices": [
            "Jrimbhikagrama (Jamui)",
            "Kundgram (Vaishali)",
            "Rajgriha (Rajgir)",
            "Bodh Gaya"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Triratna or Three Jewels i.e. right knowledge, right faith and right action are related to which of the following?",
        "answer": "Jainism",
        "choices": [
            "Jainism",
            "Buddhism",
            "Hinduism",
            "Christianity"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which of the following is the earliest holy book of Jain?",
        "answer": "Fourteen Purvas",
        "choices": [
            "Fourteen Purvas",
            "Fourteen Uppurva",
            "Twelve angas",
            "Twelve Upangas"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Who was the first disciple of Lord Mahavira",
        "answer": "Jamali",
        "choices": [
            "Jamali",
            "Yashoda",
            "Bipin",
            "Prabhash"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Ajivika sect was founded by",
        "answer": "Makkhali Gosala",
        "choices": [
            "Makkhali Gosala",
            "Anand",
            "Rahulabhadra ",
            "Upali"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Who used the caves of Barabar as their shelter-house?",
        "answer": "Ajivikas",
        "choices": [
            "Ajivikas",
            "Jains",
            "Tantrikas",
            "Buddhists"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Who of the following kings was strongly inclined towards Jainism?",
        "answer": "Kharavela",
        "choices": [
            "Kharavela",
            "Dasaratha",
            "Brihadrath",
            "Huvishk"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Gorathagiri in the Barabar Hills was conquered by",
        "answer": "Kharavela",
        "choices": [
            "Kharavela",
            "Rajaraja Chola",
            "Menander",
            "Pushyamitra Sunga"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Nathpanthis, Siddhas and Yogis made devotional religion popular in",
        "answer": "Northern India",
        "choices": [
            "Northern India",
            "Southern India",
            "Eastern India",
            "Western India"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Who contributes the most in the development of Bhagavata sect?",
        "answer": "Gupta",
        "choices": [
            "Gupta",
            "Persian",
            "Indo-Greek people",
            "Kushan"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "In ancient times, the area to the south of the Ganga was known as",
        "answer": "Magadh",
        "choices": [
            "Magadh",
            "Chola",
            "Anarta",
            "Takshashila"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which was the first capital of ancient Mahajanapada Magadh?",
        "answer": "Rajgriha (Rajgir)",
        "choices": [
            "Rajgriha (Rajgir)",
            "Pataliputra (Patna)",
            "Vaishali",
            "Anga"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which ruler founded the beautiful city, Pataliputra?",
        "answer": "Ajatashatru",
        "choices": [
            "Ajatashatru",
            "Bimbisara",
            "Bindusara",
            "Udayin"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "By which ruler Pataliputra was chosen as a capital for the first time?",
        "answer": "Udayin",
        "choices": [
            "Udayin",
            "Ajatashatru",
            "Kalashoka",
            "Kanishka"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "According to Mahavamsa, Bimbisara ascended the throne at the age of ",
        "answer": "15 years",
        "choices": [
            "15 years",
            "18 years",
            "20 years",
            "12 years"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "In which century did the first Magadhan Empire rise?",
        "answer": "6th centurey BCE",
        "choices": [
            "6th centurey BCE",
            "4th centurey BCE",
            "7th centurey BCE",
            "5th centurey BCE"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Magadha and Anga plains are part of which of the following?",
        "answer": "Middle Ganga Valley",
        "choices": [
            "Middle Ganga Valley",
            "Upper Ganga Valley",
            "Lower Ganga Valley",
            "Lower Brahmputra Valley"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Where was the world's first republican system in the 6th century BCE?",
        "answer": "Vaishali",
        "choices": [
            "Vaishali",
            "Athens",
            "Pataliputra",
            "Spata"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "The list of sixteen Mahajanapadas is available in",
        "answer": "Anguttar Nikaya",
        "choices": [
            "Anguttar Nikaya",
            "Mahabharata",
            "Chandogya Upanishad",
            "Samyukta Nikaya"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "What was the name of the dynasty of Ajatashatru?",
        "answer": "Haryanka",
        "choices": [
            "Haryanka",
            "Maurya",
            "Gupta",
            "Nanda"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Who was the physician of Magadha ruler Bimbisara?",
        "answer": "Jeevaka",
        "choices": [
            "Jeevaka",
            "Shilabhadra",
            "Vijayaena",
            "Manu"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which dynasty did rule over Magadha after Nanda Dynasty?",
        "answer": "Maurya",
        "choices": [
            "Maurya",
            "Shunga",
            "Gupta",
            "Kushan"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Who was the last king of Karnata dynasty?",
        "answer": "Harisimhadev",
        "choices": [
            "Harisimhadev",
            "Ramsimhadev",
            "Nanyadeva",
            "Narsimhadeva"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which one of the following rulers of the Magadha was the contemporary of Alexander?",
        "answer": "Dhanananda",
        "choices": [
            "Dhanananda",
            "Mahapadmananda",
            "Sukalpa",
            "Chandragupta Maurya"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "The first empire was established by which ruler in India?",
        "answer": "Chandragupta Maurya",
        "choices": [
            "Chandragupta Maurya",
            "Ashoka",
            "Kanishka",
            "Chandragupta II - Vikramaditya"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Chandragupta Maurya figures prominently in the book of",
        "answer": "Vishakhadatta",
        "choices": [
            "Vishakhadatta",
            "Bhasa",
            "Surdraka",
            "Ashvaghosha"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Who recognised Sandoorkottos as Chandragupta Maurya?",
        "answer": "William Jones",
        "choices": [
            "William Jones",
            "V. Smith",
            "R. K. Mukharjee",
            "D. R. Bhandarkar"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Chandragupta's palace situated at Pataliputra is mainly made up of",
        "answer": "Woods",
        "choices": [
            "Woods",
            "Bricks",
            "Stones",
            "Clay"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Who amongst the following Mauryan rulers did conquer the Deccan?",
        "answer": "Chandragupta Maurya",
        "choices": [
            "Chandragupta Maurya",
            "Ashoka",
            "Bindusara",
            "Kunala"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which book describe Bindusara as an anointed Kshtriya?",
        "answer": "Divyadana",
        "choices": [
            "Divyadana",
            "Rajatarangini",
            "Arthashastra",
            "Indica"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "The inscription which proves Chandragupta's sway over western India is",
        "answer": "Junagarh Rock Inscription of Rudradaman",
        "choices": [
            "Junagarh Rock Inscription of Rudradaman",
            "Kalinga Rock Inscriptions",
            "Girnar Rock Inscription of Ashoka",
            "Sopara Rock Inscription of Ashoka"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which one territory of the following was not a part of Ashoka's empire?",
        "answer": "Sri Lanka",
        "choices": [
            "Sri Lanka",
            "Afghanistan",
            "Bihar",
            "Kalinga"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "A Buddhist Council during the reign of  Ashoka was held at",
        "answer": "Pataliputra",
        "choices": [
            "Pataliputra",
            "Vaishali",
            "Rajgir",
            "Kanauj"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Language used in the incription of Ashoka is ",
        "answer": "Prakrit",
        "choices": [
            "Prakrit",
            "Sanskrit",
            "Pali",
            "Hindi"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which one of the following scripts of ancient India was written from right to left?",
        "answer": "Kharosthi",
        "choices": [
            "Kharosthi",
            "Brahmi",
            "Devanagri",
            "Kaithi"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Who first discovered the Brahmi script?",
        "answer": "James Prinsep",
        "choices": [
            "James Prinsep",
            "A Cunningham",
            "A. H. Dani",
            "Buhler"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "The name by which Ashoka is referred to in his incriptions is",
        "answer": "Priyadarshi",
        "choices": [
            "Priyadarshi",
            "Chakravarti",
            "Dharamadeva",
            "Dharmakirti"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "The only pillar on which Ashoka declares himself as the emperor of Magadha",
        "answer": "Bhabru Pillar",
        "choices": [
            "Bhabru Pillar",
            "Minor Pillar of Maski",
            "Rummindei Pillar",
            "Queen Pillar"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Megasthenes was the ambassador of",
        "answer": "Seleucus I Nicator",
        "choices": [
            "Seleucus I Nicator",
            "Alexander",
            "Darius",
            "Napolean"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "In how many categories did Megasthenes divide the Indian society?",
        "answer": "Seven",
        "choices": [
            "Seven",
            "Six",
            "Five",
            "Four"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "The division of Mauryan society into seven classes is particularly mentioned in",
        "answer": "The Indica of Megasthenes",
        "choices": [
            "The Indica of Megasthenes",
            "Kautilya's Arthashastra",
            "Ashokan Rock Edicts",
            "The Puranas"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "The description of the administration of Pataliputra is available in",
        "answer": "The Indica of Megasthenes",
        "choices": [
            "The Indica of Megasthenes",
            "Kautilya's Arthashastra",
            "Ashokan Rock Edicts",
            "Divyanadan"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "What is the name of Megasthenes book?",
        "answer": "Indica",
        "choices": [
            "Indica",
            "Rig Veda",
            "Purana",
            "Economics"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Who was the author of Indica?",
        "answer": "Megasthenes",
        "choices": [
            "Megasthenes",
            "Deimachus",
            "Vishnugupta",
            "Pliny"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "The last Mauryan emperor was",
        "answer": "Brihadratha",
        "choices": [
            "Brihadratha",
            "Jaloka",
            "Avanti Verma",
            "Nandi Vardhana"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "The decline of the Mauryan Empire was largely due to the economic consequences of Ashoka's policy. Who believed in this fact?",
        "answer": "Romila Thapar",
        "choices": [
            "Romila Thapar",
            "V. A. Smith",
            "D. N. Jha",
            "H. C. Raychaudhari"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Pradyota was the king of",
        "answer": "Avanti",
        "choices": [
            "Avanti",
            "Kasi",
            "Koshala",
            "Magadha"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which inscription tells about the various achievements of Rudraman-I?",
        "answer": "Junagadh",
        "choices": [
            "Junagadh",
            "Bhitari",
            "Nasik",
            "Sanchi"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "According to the rock inscription in Sanskrit, composed around 2nd Century CE, Sudarshan Lake, an artificial reservoir, was repaired by",
        "answer": "Rudradaman",
        "choices": [
            "Rudradaman",
            "Harsha",
            "Kanishka",
            "Ashoka"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Who among the following first issued gold coins on a large scale?",
        "answer": "Vima Kadphises",
        "choices": [
            "Vima Kadphises",
            "Pushyamitra Shunga",
            "Menander",
            "Gautamiputra Satkarni"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which dynasty ruled over India after Shunga dynasty?",
        "answer": "Kanva",
        "choices": [
            "Kanva",
            "Satvahana",
            "Gupta",
            "Kushan"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Art of Gandhara style flourished during the reign of",
        "answer": "Kushans",
        "choices": [
            "Kushans",
            "Guptas",
            "Mauryas",
            "Kanvas"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "King Kharavela is related to",
        "answer": "Hathigumpha Inscription",
        "choices": [
            "Hathigumpha Inscription",
            "Piller inscription of Girnar",
            "Pillar inscription of Junagarh",
            "Sarnath Inscription"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Kaling king Kharavel was related to ",
        "answer": "Mahameghavahana / Chedi Dynasty",
        "choices": [
            "Mahameghavahana / Chedi Dynasty",
            "Satvahana Dynasty",
            "Rath-Bhojak Dynasty",
            "Maurya Dynasty"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which Gupta ruler assumed the throne after killing his elder brother?",
        "answer": "Chandragupta II - Vikramaditya",
        "choices": [
            "Chandragupta II - Vikramaditya",
            "Shri Gupta",
            "Samudragupta",
            "Skandagupta"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Who is called the Napolean of Ancient India?",
        "answer": "Samudragupta",
        "choices": [
            "Samudragupta",
            "Shri Gupta",
            "Chandragupta Maurya",
            "Pushyamitra Sunga"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "According to Chinese source, Meghavarman, the ruler of Sri Lanka, sent a missionary to which of the following Gupta Kings for permission to build a Buddhist temple at Gaya?",
        "answer": "Samudragupta",
        "choices": [
            "Samudragupta",
            "Chandragupta I",
            "Chandragupta II - Vikramaditya",
            "Shir Gupta"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "The Gupta emperor who defeated the Hunas was",
        "answer": "Skandagupta",
        "choices": [
            "Skandagupta",
            "Chandragupta I",
            "Samudragupta",
            "Chandragupta II - Vikramaditya"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which Gupta ruler is mentioned as Param Bhagawata in Nalanda Copper Plates?",
        "answer": "Samudragupta",
        "choices": [
            "Samudragupta",
            "Chandragupta I",
            "Chandragupta II - Vikramaditya",
            "Skandagupta"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "In Pre-Gupta times, a large number of lead coins were issued by the",
        "answer": "Satavahanas",
        "choices": [
            "Satavahanas",
            "Shakas",
            "Kushans",
            "Mauryas"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "The gradual decline of towns was an important feature of which period?",
        "answer": "Gupta period",
        "choices": [
            "Gupta period",
            "Pratihara era",
            "Rashtrakut era",
            "Satavahana era"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which ruling dynasty donated maximum villages to temples and Brahmins?",
        "answer": "Gupta Dynasty",
        "choices": [
            "Gupta Dynasty",
            "Pala Dynasty",
            "Rashtrakuta",
            "Pratihara"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "What was the land revenue rate in Gupta age?",
        "answer": "Sixth part of the production",
        "choices": [
            "Sixth part of the production",
            "tenth part of the production",
            "half part of the production",
            "third part of the production"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "What is the land revenue rate in religious books?",
        "answer": "One-sixth",
        "choices": [
            "One-sixth",
            "One-eighth",
            "One-third",
            "One-fourth"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which type of land was called Aprahat",
        "answer": "Without cultivated forest land",
        "choices": [
            "Without cultivated forest land",
            "Irrigated land",
            "Dense Forest Land",
            "Cultivated Land"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Chinese traveller Sungyun or Song Yun came to India during",
        "answer": "518 to 521 CE",
        "choices": [
            "518 to 521 CE",
            "525 to 5529 CE",
            "545 to 552 CE",
            "592 to 597 CE"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "The account of the Moroccan traveller Ibn Battuta is known as",
        "answer": "Rihla",
        "choices": [
            "Rihla",
            "Tarikh-i-Rashidi",
            "Subh-u'l-Asha",
            "Riyaz-us-salatin"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which of the following philosophies of India propounded the atom theory?",
        "answer": "Vaisheshika",
        "choices": [
            "Vaisheshika",
            "Nyaya",
            "Sankhya",
            "Yoga"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Who has written the Harshacharita",
        "answer": "Banabhatta",
        "choices": [
            "Banabhatta",
            "Aryabhatta",
            "Vishnugupta",
            "Parimalgupta"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Who laid the foundation of Vardhana Dynasty?",
        "answer": "Pushyabhuti",
        "choices": [
            "Pushyabhuti",
            "Rajyavardhana",
            "Harshavardhana",
            "Prabhakarvardhana"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which Chinese traveller visited India during Haravardhana's rule?",
        "answer": "Hiuen-Tsang",
        "choices": [
            "Hiuen-Tsang",
            "Fa-Hien",
            "I-Tsing",
            "Taranath"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "The famous Chinese pilgrim Fa-Hien visited India during the reign of",
        "answer": "Chandragupta II - Vikramaditya",
        "choices": [
            "Chandragupta II - Vikramaditya",
            "Harshavardhana",
            "Ramagupta",
            "Chandragupta I"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "During Hiuen-Tsang tour in India most famous city for the production of cotton clothes was",
        "answer": "Mathura",
        "choices": [
            "Mathura",
            "Varanasi",
            "Pataliputra",
            "Kanchi"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Chinese traveller Hiuen-Tsang studied at which univesity",
        "answer": "Nalanda",
        "choices": [
            "Nalanda",
            "Taxilla",
            "Vikramshila",
            "Uddandapura"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Chinese traveller I-tsing was on the tour of Bihar in about",
        "answer": "671 CE",
        "choices": [
            "671 CE",
            "405 CE",
            "635 CE",
            "637 CE"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Nalanda Vihar was destroyed by",
        "answer": "Bakhtiyar Khalji",
        "choices": [
            "Bakhtiyar Khalji",
            "Qutubuddin Aibak",
            "Muhammad Bin Tughlaq",
            "Alauddin Khalji"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Who was the real founder of Turk rule in Bihar?",
        "answer": "Bakhtiyar Khalji",
        "choices": [
            "Bakhtiyar Khalji",
            "Malik Husarnuddin",
            "Ibrahim",
            "Dariya Khan Noohani"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "How many rulers of Aryavarta have been mentioned in 21st line of Allahabad Pillar Inscription?",
        "answer": "Nine",
        "choices": [
            "Nine",
            "Eight",
            "Seven",
            "Six"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Who has argued that the Gupta and post-Gupta periods saw a decline in the money economy?",
        "answer": "R. S. Sharma",
        "choices": [
            "R. S. Sharma",
            "R. S. Tripathi",
            "Radha Kumud Mookerjee",
            "D. C. Sircar"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Who was the ruler of India during the 7th cneture CE known for his patronage of Buddhism and support for cultural activities?",
        "answer": "Harsha",
        "choices": [
            "Harsha",
            "Ashoka",
            "Chandragupta Maurya",
            "Vikramaditya"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "The associates of Khajuraho Temple Architecture were",
        "answer": "Chandela",
        "choices": [
            "Chandela",
            "Chahamana",
            "Gurjara-Pratihara",
            "Paramara"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "The attractive doors of the temples of South India are called",
        "answer": "Gopuram",
        "choices": [
            "Gopuram",
            "Shikhara",
            "Devalaya",
            "Mandapam"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Who established trade relations with Roman empire?",
        "answer": "Cheras",
        "choices": [
            "Cheras",
            "Kushanas",
            "Western Shakas",
            "Vakatakas"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "The Chola age was most famous for",
        "answer": "Village Assemblies",
        "choices": [
            "Village Assemblies",
            "Trade with Ceylon",
            "Advancement in Tamil Culture",
            "War with the Rashtrakutas"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Who was the founder of Chola Dynasty?",
        "answer": "Vijayalaya",
        "choices": [
            "Vijayalaya",
            "Karikal",
            "Aditya I",
            "Rajaraja I"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which of the following dynasties is not mentioned in Sangam literature?",
        "answer": "Kadamb",
        "choices": [
            "Kadamb",
            "Chola",
            "Chera",
            "Pandya"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Why was uraiyur famous in Sangam Era?",
        "answer": "Important trade centre of cotton",
        "choices": [
            "Important trade centre of cotton",
            "Important trade centre of spices",
            "Important trade centre of domestic trade",
            "Important trade centre of foreign trade"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Who was the writer of Mudrarakshasa?",
        "answer": "Vishakhadatta",
        "choices": [
            "Vishakhadatta",
            "Aswaghosha",
            "Kalidasa",
            "Bhasa"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Kumarsambhavam an epic poem was composed by",
        "answer": "Kalidasa",
        "choices": [
            "Kalidasa",
            "Banabhatta",
            "Harishena",
            "Chanda Bardai"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "What is the name of Kalhana's book?",
        "answer": "Rajtarangini",
        "choices": [
            "Rajtarangini",
            "Arthashastra",
            "Indica",
            "Purana"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "The author of Swapanavasavadatta is",
        "answer": "Bhasa",
        "choices": [
            "Bhasa",
            "Kalidasa",
            "Bhavabhutti",
            "Rajashekhara"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Who wrote the book Kiratarjuniya?",
        "answer": "Bharavi",
        "choices": [
            "Bharavi",
            "Bhatti",
            "Shudrak",
            "Kalidasa"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Epigraphic records (Inscriptions) suggest that in ancient India, the rulers of Bihar had contact with",
        "answer": "Java-Sumatra",
        "choices": [
            "Java-Sumatra",
            "Thailand",
            "Burma",
            "Cambodia"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which ruler of Bengal founded the ancient University called Vikramshila",
        "answer": "Dharampala",
        "choices": [
            "Dharampala",
            "Gopala",
            "Devpala",
            "Mahipala"
        ]
    }
]